All right, so reconstruction made
promises to black Americans and Jim Crow
went ahead and broke those promises. But
fear not my dear pupil because it's the
1940s and 50s and that means that the
civil rights movement is starting to
pull up its big boy civil rights reform
pants and slap that grin right off of
Jim Crow's face. So if you're ready to
get them brain cows milked, let's get to
it. Okay, so in the post-war years black
Americans mounted a massive push for
equal rights and the end of racial
discrimination in the United States. And
like I said, much of the energy for this
push came from the promises made to
black Americans in the reconstruction
era and then broken soon thereafter. Oh,
what's that? You want some examples?
You know I got you, boo. So recall that
after the Civil War slavery was
abolished by the 13th Amendment and a
Republican-dominated Congress passed
sweeping legislation intended to
recognize the full rights of America's
black citizens. And then states went
ahead and ratified two more
constitutional amendments, namely the
14th Amendment which protected citizens
from the infringement of their civil
rights by state governments and the 15th
Amendment which recognized the right of
black men to vote. And then to further
get the reconstruction civil rights
party thumping, Congress passed the
Civil Rights Act of 1875 which
guaranteed black citizens equal access
to public facilities and transportation
and jury service. And all of that taken
together meant that black Americans
everywhere could prop their feet up and
throw back their heads in laughter and
proclaim, "Man, it is good to be black
in America." And if you can't smell the
rank sarcasm dripping off of that last
sentence, then my dear pupil, you must
have fallen asleep for the last two
units. So wake up and let me remind you
that despite these legislative
victories, nearly every gain made by
black Americans in the reconstruction
era was systematically diminished or
altogether undone by cranky white
southerners and white northerners who
simply didn't want to be bothered with
efforts towards racial equality. For
example, although slavery was formally
abolished, an eerily similar arrangement
took its place, namely sharecropping,
which had the effect of keeping black
southerners poor and dependent on white
planters. And then the Supreme Court
went ahead and dropped a huge steamer on
the Civil Rights Act and declared it
unconstitutional. And as a result,
southern states got real busy passing a
series of Jim Crow laws which built an
enduring apparatus for maintaining
racial segregation in the South. And
under the Jim Crow system, southern
states disenfranchised black voters by
introducing poll taxes and literacy
tests and the infamous grandfather
clause. Additionally, the Supreme
Court's establishment of the separate
but equal doctrine in the Plessy v.
Ferguson case enabled Southern states to
segregate every conceivable public
service between the white and black
races. Not to mention there was the
ongoing horrific violence of black
lynching for which white perpetrators
operated largely without fear of legal
ramifications. And so the point is the
grand promises of racial equality that
were made during Reconstruction had so
far gone largely unfulfilled, which is
why historian Eric Foner calls
Reconstruction an unfinished revolution.
But during the 1940s and 50s, black
Americans made significant strides to
claim the equality that had been
promised but so far denied. And I cannot
wait to tell you about that, but first
let me say this. A lot of you guys asked
me with desperation in your voices where
the whole unit reviews are for units 5
through 9. The first four are here on
YouTube, but in your frantic clicking
around my channel you just can't find
them. That's because they only exist in
my A push Heimler review guide, which
has everything you need to study as fast
as possible for that big hairy national
exam in May. So if that's something
you're into, check that link in the
description. All right, so now let's get
to the spicy meat of this topic and talk
about some of the first major steps
taken in the civil rights movement
during the 40s and 50s and there are two
that I'll mention by name. First of all,
during World War II a group of black and
white activists in Chicago founded the
Congress of Racial Equality, which
organized highly visible efforts to
challenge racial segregation by means of
nonviolent action. And during the war,
CORE supported the wider double V
campaign in which black Americans
demonstrated to secure a double victory,
one over fascists abroad and another
over racist at home. And chief among
their demands was the elimination of
racial discrimination in hiring
practices and the abolishment of poll
taxes and other voter discrimination
tactics. And then perhaps CORE's most
enduring act was to organize the Journey
of Reconciliation in 1947 in which eight
white men and eight black men rode
segregated buses through several
Southern states to challenge laws that
mandated segregation on public
transportation. Now six of the men were
ultimately arrested, but their
demonstration gained a significant
amount of press and thus laid the
groundwork for similar nonviolent
protests regarding public
transportation, the most notable of
which was the Montgomery bus boycott in
1955 and the more widespread ride-ins
that occurred in the 1960s. And then
second, while CORE and other activist
groups organized grassroots protest
campaigns, lawyers in the NAACP, most
notably Thurgood Marshall and Charles
Hamilton Houston, worked to dismantle
segregation through the courts. And
their strategy was to attack the hulking
edifice of the separate but equal
doctrine piece by piece rather than
trying to destroy the entire structure
at once. And so to that end, the NAACP
won cases before and after the war which
focused on the unconstitutionality of
racial segregation in professional and
graduate school. And these smaller
victories would ultimately lay the
foundation for the much larger and
sweeping victory in Brown v. Board of
Education, of which I shall have more to
say in a moment. But for now, you're
going to need to know that as these
grassroots demonstrations grew and
became more visible, they put serious
pressure on the federal government to
bend an ear to the demands of black
Americans. And all three branches of the
federal government actually took action
to respond to some of these demands. But
the government's motivation was kind of
a mixed bag. Like for sure, some
politicians pushed for equality simply
because it was the just and
constitutional thing to do. But others
were more worried about what black
inequality meant for America's image on
the world stage. For example, the
Soviets were more than happy to
highlight all this racial tension and
inequality and point out that the United
States claimed to be the leader of the
free world and in that way, the math
didn't really matter. And even more to
the point, communism's most attractive
feature was that it promised equality
for the marginalized. And so all that
together got all three branches of
government moving to correct some of
these issues. So let's talk about it.
And let's start with the sassiest of all
branches, the executive branch. So
members of the NAACP petitioned
President Truman directly to address
racial violence and black
disenfranchisement. And their pressure
campaign eventually worked. In 1946,
Truman issued an executive order that
created the Committee on Civil Rights
and its members were tasked with
investigating infringements on American
civil rights and to make policy
proposals for combating any injustices
that they discovered. And so the
Committee reported to Truman many
inequalities suffered by black Americans
and suggested a broad range of
legislation that might make good on the
promises of reconstruction. And one
particularly notable action that Truman
took in response to these findings was
to issue an executive order that
desegregated the military. Okay, noise,
but what's happening with the judicial
branch? Well, standing on the strength
of their mounting judicial victories,
the legal team of the NAACP argued its
most significant set of cases dealing
with segregation in public schools. Now,
recall that Thurgood Marshall and his
team had already secured victories in
desegregating graduate and professional
schools. But now they argue that in
order for black Americans to have a
reasonable chance to enter higher
education at all, they needed to receive
a robust primary education first, and
school segregation prevented that. And
so, they argued that by consigning black
children to separate but equal schools,
state governments were violating these
children's 14th Amendment provision for
equal protection under the law, since
separation by its very nature was
unequal. And therefore, in 1954, the
court issued its landmark decision in
Brown v. the Board of Education,
declaring that school segregation was
indeed unconstitutional, thus
overturning the Plessy decision and
laying the foundation for the
desegregation of schools. However,
here's where I tell you that black
students still faced stiff resistance
from Southern states who were in no mood
to integrate their schools. And that
resistance meant that whatever gains
were made in the arena of racial
equality came at an exceedingly slow
pace. that sluggishness wasn't helped in
the slightest by the wording of the
Supreme Court's decision that schools
must be integrated with, quote, all
deliberate speed. And you know, you see
the problem, right? Speed obviously
means go fast, like integrate those
schools quick, fast, and in a hurry. But
deliberate has the sense of slowing down
and carefully considering a decision.
And so, that little lexical loophole was
all the Southern states needed to drag
their feet on integration. Hey look, I
want to integrate these schools right
this minute, but that gum Chief Justice
Earl Warren told me to deliberate. So,
I'm going to sit here and deliberate
about how fast I want to go.
Give me about 10 years and get back to
me. Now, in 1957, one particularly
high-profile case of school integration
occurred in Little Rock, Arkansas.
There, nine black students enrolled to
attend classes at Central High School,
and in response, Arkansas Governor Orval
Faubus went ahead and sent the stinking
National Guard to block their entrance.
But President Eisenhower, in no mood to
abide such state-level sass and the
blatant flouting of federal law, took
control of the National Guard and sent
additional federal troops to to that
these students, who became known as the
Little Rock Nine could attend school
safely. And finally, let's see how the
legislative branch was handling civil
rights. So, the Brown ruling energized
civil rights activists and emboldened
them to make even greater demands of
their government for equality. So, in
response to that pressure, Congress
passed the Civil Rights Act of 1957,
which was the first major civil rights
legislation signed since Reconstruction.
This law primarily aimed to protect
black voting rights, particularly in the
South, where such rights were under
significant threat. However, several
Southern senators mounted a vicious
campaign to significantly weaken this
law's provisions. For example, one
amendment added that anyone found
violating black Americans voting rights
must be subject to a jury trial in order
to be convicted. And since it was nigh
unto guaranteed that a white official
violating the law would sit before an
all-white jury, the amendment and others
like it significantly weakened the
voting rights protection afforded by the
law. And just for poops and giggles, let
me mention that when this bill came up
for debate in the Senate, South Carolina
Senator Strom Thurmond clocked the
longest filibuster on record in order to
secure the amendments that I just
mentioned. The man spoke for 24 hours
and 18 minutes, which means that this
guy hated the idea of black equality so
much that he flapped his mouth hole for
more than a day and peed in a bucket
situated in a closet just off the Senate
floor. What a fun guy. Okay, you can
click here to watch all my other Unit 8
videos, or you can click here to grab my
A Push timeline review guide, which has
everything you need to study as fast as
possible. I'm glad you came around, and
I'll catch you on the flip flop. I'm
Larout.